For more information: https://dsevero.com

# **INTERESTS**

BIO & RESEARCH Broadly, my interests are information theory, generative modeling, and data compression. Current compression algorithms are not well suited to handle structured and high-dimensional data, such as images and graphs. I'm interested in building computationally efficient entropy coders that can be used with deep generative models. I have 5 years of industry experience applying machine learning to real-world problems, as well as open-source contributions to large projects such as Dask and NeuralCompression.

## **EDUCATION**

## University of Toronto

Electrical & Computer Engineering - Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) Started Fall 2020 - Undergraduate Exchange Program (1 year) 2013 - 2014

# Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil Bachelor of Science in Electronics Engineering First Class Honours, 99th percentile.

RESEARCH

# Facebook AI Research (FAIR)

New York, Summer 2021

2010 - 2015

Research Scientist Intern with Karen Ullrich EXPERIENCE

#### Vector Institute for AI

Toronto, 2020 - Current

Ph.D. Student Researcher with Alireza Makhzani

## **PUBLICATIONS**

Reys, Arthur D., Danilo Silva, Daniel Severo, et al.: Predicting Multiple ICD-10 Codes from Brazilian-Portuguese Clinical Notes. Accepted at BRACIS 2020. arXiv: 2008.01515 [cs.CL].

Ruan\*, Yangjun, Karen Ullrich\*, Daniel Severo\*, et al.: Improving Lossless Compression Rates via Monte Carlo Bits-Back Coding. Accepted at ICML 2021 as a long talk. arXiv: 2102.11086 [cs.LG].

Severo, Daniel, Elad Domanovitz, and Ashish Khisti: Regularized Classification-Aware Quantization. Accepted at BSC 2021. arXiv: 2107.09716 [cs.LG].

# **PREPRINTS**

Severo, Daniel, Flávio Amaro, Estevam R. Hruschka Jr, et al.: Ward2ICU: A Vital Signs Dataset of Inpatients from the General Ward. 2019. arXiv: 1910.00752 [cs.LG].

Severo\*, Daniel, James Townsend\*, Ashish Khisti, et al.: Compressing Multisets with Large Alphabets. 2021. arXiv: 2107.09202 [cs.IT].

#### AWARDS

#### Vector Scholarship in AI Recipient 2020-21

2020

The Vector Scholarship in AI supports the recruitment of top students to AI-related master's programs in Ontario and is valued at \$17,500.

https://vectorinstitute.ai/aimasters

#### NSERC Applied Research Rapid Response to COVID-19 Grant 2020 Our project titled "Canadian Hospital Simulator For Management of COVID19 Cases and Contact Tracing" was awarded \$75,000.00. https://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/Innovate-Innover/CCI-COVID\_eng.asp

## Virtual Design Challenge Winner

2019

Won 1st place at the VDC hosted by The University of British Columbia with my paper *Proof of Novelty*. Received a cash prize of \$3,000.

https://github.com/dsevero/Proof-of-Novelty

#### Student Merit Award and Medal

2015

Graduated with the highest GPA ever obtained (at the time) for my major. Elected "Best Student" by the faculty of Electrical & Electronics Engineering at the Federal University of Santa Catarina.

## Science Without Borders Scholarship

2013

2010 - 2013

Awarded a full scholarship that covered tuition, transportation, necessary materials and living costs to study 2 academic semesters at the University of Toronto.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### Federal University of Santa Catarina - Teaching Assistant

- Communications Theory Fall and Winter 2015
- Introduction to Electronics Fall and Winter 2013

- Single-Variable Calculus Fall 2010

CERTI Foundation - Programming Instructor

# OPEN SOURCE CONTRIBUTIONS

## **Neural Compression**

- https://github.com/facebookresearch/NeuralCompression

#### Dask & Dask-ML

- https://github.com/dask/dask/pulls?q=author:dsevero

- https://github.com/dask/dask-ml/pulls?q=author:dsevero

## OTHER PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

3778 Healthcare - Machine Learning Engineer2018 - 2020Linx Impulse - Head of Data Science2016 - 2018CERTI Foundation - Research Engineer2015 - 2016Wavetech Technology - Embedded Systems Intern2015CERTI Foundation - Electrical Engineering Intern2010 - 2013WEG Industries - Electrical Engineering InternSummers 2011 and 2012

### REFERENCES

### Prof. Ashish Khisti

University of Toronto

Professor and Canada Research Chair (Tier II)
Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering
https://www.comm.utoronto.ca/~akhisti/

#### Prof. Alireza Makhzani

Vector Institute

Faculty member at the Vector Institute for Artificial Intelligence Adjunct Professor and Canada CIFAR AI Chair

Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering

http://www.alireza.ai/

# Karen Ullrich, Ph.D.

Facebook AI Research (FAIR)

Research Scientist

https://karenullrich.info/

## James Townsend, Ph.D.

University College London

https://j-towns.github.io/

# Prof. Frank R. Kschischang

University of Toronto

Distinguished Professor of Digital Communication Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering

https://www.comm.utoronto.ca/frank/